<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The middle-way of perfection with indifferency between the orthodox and the Quaker by J.H.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7480</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13513501</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13513501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99861</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45141)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99861)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 791:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The middle-way of perfection with indifferency between the orthodox and the Quaker by J.H.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Humfrey.  Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99861:1"/>
            <p>THE Middle-Way. OF PERFECTION. With Indifferency between The ORTHODOX AND THE QUAKER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> J. H.</p>
            <q>Doing nothing by Partiality,</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Bible and Three Crowns in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:99861:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99861:2"/>
            <head>Of Perfection.</head>
            <p>PErfection is one of the Doctrines of the Quaker, that there is <hi>a ſtate of perfect ſeparation from ſin</hi> in this life; That it is not onely poſſible for a man to keep the whole Law of God, but that every true Chriſtian doth attain it; That the work of Chriſts Redemption does conſiſt in this to bring men up to ſuch a ſtate, to be free not onely in regard of the <hi>guilt,</hi> but the <hi>inhabitaton</hi> of ſin, ſo that it is not indeed ſo much pardoned, as aboliſhed. There are no mean Doctors in the Schools have gone before them and taught us, that though there remain that which is <hi>fomes pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati</hi> (to uſe <hi>Auguſtines</hi> expreſſion); yet not that which is <hi>pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum</hi> in the regenerate after Baptiſme, and conſequently the righteouſneſs which they through Chriſt (or grace) perform (the Quaker chooſes to call it Chriſts Righteouſneſs) being perfect, does not onely conſtitute them juſt in the ſight of God, but enables them to ſtand before the Throne of Gods juſtice, and ſo juſtifyes them and ſaves them. They now who are read here in the Controverſies between us and the Papiſts, may gueſs how far theſe friends are like to be ſupported; and that they are not therefore to be put off, as ſome think, with ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and contempt onely. For my part, I will confeſs it is not the deſigne of theſe Papers to endeavour ſo much a refutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any Party, as to build up others in that Truth which Errour on all ſides leanes upon. <hi>Omne falſum innititur vero.</hi> And as the beſt Phyſitians have been noted ſometimes to take
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99861:3"/>very great regard to the ordinary receipts of old women and the meaneſt perſons: ſo will it become the modeſt Divine, to endeavour rather to <hi>diſcover</hi> and ſift out that Truth which lies in his Adverſaries meaning, then to <hi>expoſe,</hi> and ſhame their Opinions.</p>
            <p>Before I come to my preſent ſubject, it is neceſſary that I ſet a <hi>little</hi> out of my way, which may elſe engender diſpute, in my laſt paper. It is about pardon of ſin, which I take to be the <hi>effect,</hi> not <hi>formal Reaſon</hi> of juſtification. <hi>Pardon</hi> (ſayes Mr. Bradſhaw) <hi>is neither the whole, nor any eſſential part of juſtification, but onely a contingent effect of it.</hi> Treat. of Juſt. c. 8. That a man muſt repent and believe (which is to perform the condition of the Covenant of Grace), in order of nature, before he be pardoned, is out of queſtion. That God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the perſon a performer who is ſo, ariſes of neceſſity, becauſe his judgment is alwayes according to Truth. Now when Gods accounting a man Righteous according to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant (which is all one with his accounting him a penitent Believer, or performer of the condition) is <hi>juſtifying</hi> him as I ſay there, and pardon followes this, it appeared to me that Remiſſion muſt not be the <hi>form</hi> it ſelf, or <hi>part,</hi> but the <hi>effect</hi> of juſtification. And it is true remiſſion is the effect, and no part of <hi>this</hi> juſtification: But there may be ſome <hi>other</hi> or further juſtification then this. To avoyd needleſs difference therefore with Brethren, I muſt diſtinguiſh juſtification. Juſtification we agree to be a forenſical act oppoſed to the laying any thing to a mans charge whereby he may be condemned. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect? It is God that juſtifieth.</hi> Now there is a double charge, the charge of the <hi>Law,</hi> that we are ſinners, and ſo condemnable for violation of it: And the charge of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> that we have not performed the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying condition which God requires of us for the eſcaping that condemnation. Though it be an acquittal of us from the <hi>latter</hi> charge is that juſtification which every man is ſo much concerned to provide for, as that which depends upon the plea of what himſelf does, and the acquittal of us from the <hi>former,</hi> depends onely on the plea of what Chriſt hath done for us, which can hardly ſuffer any debate I think before our Judge:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99861:3"/>yet will I not deny but juſtification may be taken ſo <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>henſively</hi> as to contain in it our diſcharge from the <hi>Law</hi> alſo There is a juſtification then in regard to a <hi>particular</hi> charge, the charge of the <hi>one:</hi> or a <hi>univerſal</hi> juſtification againſt all accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, or the charge of <hi>both.</hi> As we muſt anſwer the charge of the Goſpel by denying that charge, and pleading our perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: we anſwer the charge of the Law by confeſſing it, and pleading Chriſts ſatisfaction; that is we acknowledge that we areguilty and have deſerved Death, but yet that we are not condemnable becauſe we are pardoned by the Law of Grace, through the Meritorious Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Sacrifice of Chriſt Jeſus, ſuppoſing ſuch a Charge can find place before our Law-giver. Our Faith and Repentance is our Righteouſneſs in regard to the Goſpel: but pardon of ſin, together with this righteouſneſs, may go both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Vniverſal</hi> juſtification. I cannot indeed but ſay ſtill, that that juſtification which is <hi>particular</hi> in regard to the Goſpel Charge, ſeemes to me to be the juſtification which St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>James</hi> mainly intend, if not altogether; for when the one ſayes we are <hi>juſtified by Faith,</hi> and the other <hi>by works alſo,</hi> and both prove it from one and the ſame Text, that <hi>Abraham believed, and it was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs:</hi> I pray what elſe can juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication be with either, but Gods imputing evangelical obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to a perſon for Righteouſneſs, that is Gods accounting of him righteous upon his believeing repenting, or performing the condition of the Goſpel? That the Apoſtles <hi>Righteouſneſs without Works,</hi> and <hi>Pardon,</hi> is not the ſame (and conſquently that the one is a probation and not a deſcription of the other as I noted upon reflection), muſt be granted by thoſe who make both theſe to be parts of our juſtification, for ſuch is the nature of parts to be diverſe one from another. <hi>Haec eſt natura par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ut unum corpus diverſa componant.</hi> Boethius. de Conſ. l. 3. p. 3. Again <hi>Quod a qualibet re diverſum eſt, id non eſt illud a quo intelligitur diverſum.</hi> It muſt be alſo confeſſed by me, that the diverſity of <hi>two</hi> things, as the cauſe and effect, does not hinder thoſe things to be parts of another <hi>third</hi> which is the <hi>compoſitum</hi> of both: and conſquently that Gods juſtifiying us by this <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> (that is by <hi>Faith</hi> or Evangelical Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99861:4"/>
               <hi>without the Works of the Law</hi>), and then pardoning us, as the effect of that act, may both make up the <hi>compoſitum</hi> of <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal</hi> juſtification. You ſee how tender I am of perſiſting in any miſtake, wherein I have or may prejudice others. I doe not find that the Scripture does denominate or pronounce any one <hi>righteous</hi> or <hi>a juſt Man</hi> from one end to the other, upon any other account then his <hi>doing Righteouſneſs,</hi> yet will I not quarrel with any that ſay, we are made righteous alſo by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs; and that the delivery of us from ſin, from the Law, and condemnation by it, is <hi>Juſtification:</hi> Though really I am apt to think, that this work is to be attributed rather with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, to our <hi>Redemption.</hi> Compare <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. with other places. And ſo I come to my point, of <hi>Perfection.</hi> Only I muſt adde this Corollary. <hi>Simpliciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum nobis videtur ſi dicamus, fidem juſtiſicare, quia credenti ſua ſides imputetur ad juſtitiam. Fides antem ad juſtitiam imputari dicitur, quia Dens illum qui viva fide in Chriſtum credit pro juſto habet &amp; reputat, cum a paena peccati liberans, &amp; ad vitam aeternam acceptans, propter Chriſti mortem &amp; obedienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is to be acknowledged, that there are, and may be very many Scriptures eaſily preſſed by the Quaker and Papiſt for the ſervice of their Doctrine, ſo that there is no doubt but thus much is proved; that it is our duty to be as <hi>perfect</hi> as they would have. Every ſin is forbidden, and every good thing that is ſo by the Law of innocency, is commanded. But it is one thing to know what is our duty, and another what will be accepted of God in our performance. Our duty is one thing, and what we can, or doe attain to, another. God brings not his <hi>ſcales</hi> under the Covenant of Grace, that our works ſhould have their full weight, but his <hi>touchſtone</hi> expecting they be right, that they proceed onely from a ſincere heart, and then he accepts them upon the merits of Chriſt Jeſus. Nay indeed the <hi>Duty</hi> of the Goſpel is one thing, and the <hi>Condition</hi> of it ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The words <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>perfection</hi> in ſeveral places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, may receive an interpretation according to the purpoſe unto which they are applied. <hi>As many as are perfect, let us be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99861:4"/>thus minded.</hi> By perfection there, I apprehend ſuch a degree of knowledge, as the <hi>ſtrong</hi> Chriſtian is ſuppoſed to have other-where in oppoſition to the <hi>weake,</hi> who underſtanding not their liberty by the Goſpel were ſcandalized about indifferent things, and ſo could not walk up to the ſame rule. <hi>Not that I had already attained</hi> (ſayes the ſame Apoſtle hard by) <hi>or were already perfect.</hi> In the one verſe of the ſame Chapter he is perfect, in the other he is not; wherein yet there is no more real difficulty then this, that a man may in <hi>one thing</hi> be ſaid to be perfect, who in <hi>another</hi> is imperfect, which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſhewes in the fifteenth chapter of his ſecond book, <hi>De peccatorum meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; remiſſione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed that Father in that book and in another, <hi>De ſpiritu &amp; littera,</hi> hath the luck to treat induſtriouſly on this matter. <hi>Alia eſt quaeſtio</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>utrum eſſe poſſit homo in hac vita ſine peccato: alia utrum ſit? It is one queſtion, whether it be poſſible for a man to attain to ſuch perfection as to live without ſin? and another, whether there be any that doe?</hi> For the former queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he diſtinguiſhes of what is poſſible by <hi>Grace:</hi> And what is poſſible by our <hi>own Strength.</hi> To hold, that any man by his free will onely without grace is able to keep all Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and be without ſin, is that grand Pelagian Doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which he ſets his face, and deteſts it: But that it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to attaine this by <hi>grace,</hi> or the ſpecial aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit, he thinks it beſt (it ſeemes) to grant. He thinks it not fit, not ſafe, to ſay any (or all) of Gods Commandements are impoſſible. Beſides, where God vouchſafes his grace, the work (he pleads) is to be aſcribed to him unto whom <hi>nothing is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</hi> For the ſecond queſtion, whether there is or ever was any man upon earth (Chriſt onely excepted) that does, or did attain hereunto (how great a meaſure of grace ſoever it be which he has or had), he is peremtory in the denyal, as full in his proof from Scripture, there being ſeveral things (he ſayes) which are <hi>poſſible,</hi> and yet never ſhall <hi>be</hi> in the World.</p>
            <p>There is no doubt now but in the diſpute between the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and us the terme <hi>perfection</hi> is underſtood alike. It is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection they hold in reference to the whole life, that a man ſins
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99861:5"/>not. And if any in the diſpute do carry the matter ſo high a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as to deny what they contend for, to be <hi>poſſible,</hi> they may if they pleaſe chooſe more warineſs from St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> for the Quaker aſcribes not to themſelves, but to the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>life,</hi> the <hi>power,</hi> or to <hi>Chriſt within,</hi> all that they doe. On the contrary ſide, if theſe Friends will not be content with what is allowed them, that our duty reaches ſo far as not to ſin at all (and conſequently to be perfect as the Saints in Heaven, that is, to be in our kind as God in his, is perfect), and that it be not denied (when we cannot grant) that this our whole duty is <hi>poſſible</hi> through that ſpirit by which I hope ſome of them are lead: but they will go on further to ſay, that themſelves are ſuch as <hi>have attained,</hi> and that every one who does not attain to the ſame pitch, to wit, to live without ſin, cannot be in a ſtate of Grace and Salvation, I ſhall think it time to ſend them, if they be learned, to the ſame Father and Books, for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof and ſatisfaction. As for my thoughts farther of this <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility,</hi> and what diſtinction is here wanting, you may ſee (p. 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.) in my firſt paper of <hi>Election.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is common indeed for the Scripture to ſpeak of men and women as perfect. <hi>Mark the perfect Man.</hi> Noah was a <hi>perfect man.</hi> Job a <hi>perfect man.</hi> The good Kings are ſaid to walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God with a <hi>perfect heart,</hi> when yet their failings are recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſame chapter. It is leſs wonder, to have onr duty ſet forth in this manner. <hi>Thou ſhalt be perfect with thy Lord thy God.</hi> Let us <hi>go on unto perfection.</hi> Walk before me and <hi>be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> Thou ſhalt love the Lord with <hi>all thy heart, with all thy ſoul, with all thy ſtrength.</hi> Thy Will be done in Earth as it is done <hi>in Heaven.</hi> Be followers of Chriſt. And as <hi>his</hi> was, ſo muſt our <hi>converſation be in the world.</hi> There is no man hath a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible knowledge of himſelf, but he perceives dayly how far his <hi>duty</hi> is above his <hi>performance.</hi> I am not ignorant neither, how ſome Texts may be drawn out of their ſence, where the place muſt give them a right conſtruction. <hi>by one Offering</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>Chriſt hath perfected them that are ſanctified:</hi> But we are not to conceive that at <hi>once</hi> therefore he perfects mans ſanctification. I deny not moreover, but the end of Chriſts manifeſtation in the fleſh, was to <hi>redeem us from iniquity,</hi> to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99861:5"/>
               <hi>deſtroy the Works of the Devil,</hi> to reſtore us out of ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, and <hi>preſent us unto God,</hi> as a <hi>peculiar People, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by Faith, Zealous of good Works, Holy and without blame, Entire and wanting nothing, Perfect and compleat in all the Will of God.</hi> I will not cite here thoſe abundance of Texts which are at my pens end, leaſt it ſhould engage me to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diſcourſe concerning them. It will ſuffice in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral that we diſtinguiſh of the <hi>time,</hi> and of the <hi>perfection</hi> which is to be underſtood in ſuch ſeveral places.</p>
            <p>I do remember when the Donatiſts are pleading, many of the ſame and the like Scriptures for their Church and ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this is one anſwer the Orthodox offer them. There are <hi>duo tempora Eccleſiae</hi> (ſay they) <hi>quae nunc eſt: &amp; qualis erit. Illa divina Teſtimonia quibus commendatur eccleſia cum malorum commixtione hoc tempus ejus ſignificat qualis eſt in praeſenti ſaeculo; &amp; illa teſtimonia quibus commendatur non habere commixtos malos, illud ejus tempus, qualis venturo ſaeculo in aeternum futura eſt! See Breviculi collationum cum Donatiſtis.</hi> I ſhall ſay the ſame here. There are two Times or States of the Church. The ſtate of this <hi>preſent life,</hi> and the ſtate of the <hi>life to come.</hi> We doubt not but Chriſt hath purchaſed for his Church and People ſuch a ſtate as is to be without ſin, as well as without miſery: But this ſtate which is <hi>compleating</hi> alway, muſt not be expected to be <hi>compleated</hi> till the other life. When Chriſt ſhall preſent her to his Father, a <hi>glorious</hi> Church then ſhall ſhe be, without <hi>ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing:</hi> but while ſhe is but a <hi>gracious Church,</hi> that is, while ſhe is in this life, ſhe ſhall not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her wrinkles nor her troubles. We ſhall reconcile the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture very well, if when it ſets forth every man as a ſinner, that ſtands in need of remiſſion every day, we refer ſuch Texts as ſpeak indeed of perfect freedom, unto the ſtate of the life to come.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place then, there is <hi>perfectio viae, or patriae; viato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> or <hi>comprehenſorum,</hi> to uſe the terms of the Schools. A perfection belonging to the ſtate while we are in the way, as travellours: or a perfection belonging to the ſtate when we ſhall get home, or to our Countrey, or to ſuch as have <hi>already attained,</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> terms, I hope the Quaker that diſputes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99861:6"/>with us about <hi>Perfection,</hi> will acknowledge a difference in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of attainment between the two eſtates of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> And if that <hi>perfection</hi> which conſiſts in a freedom from all ſin does remain for the Reſt above, I ſee not who the man is, that can free himſelf from all <hi>ſinful imperfection,</hi> in this World. <hi>I preſs forward</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>if by any meanes I might attain unto the Reſurrection of the Dead.</hi> Such a Perfection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like as that <hi>in Heaven</hi> is his duty, but he can by no meanes here <hi>attaine</hi> unto it.</p>
            <p>In the next place then, that <hi>Perfection</hi> which belongs to the ſtate of this Life is to be conſidered in the <hi>kind,</hi> and in the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> of it. There is a Perfection of the <hi>kind:</hi> and of the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</hi> I do not find any of theſe friends in their writings do take Perfection for a <hi>ſuperlative</hi> Word; They acknowledge <hi>degrees</hi> in their Perfecton, that one hath more of the light and life then another. There are <hi>Fathers, young Men, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> in Grace, as St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks. The Child hath a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of parts, that is, hath all its Members, as well as the growen man, but not at the fame maturity. Now I would faine know of the judicious among this ſect two things in my way. The one, whether that degree of Holineſs which is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by any man, is not the duty of every man? The other, whether he that fails in the leaſt of what is his Dudy, does not ſin? The rule is but one to all: and ſin is any want of conformity to that Rule. However in this, we may both come to an accord. They will yield to us, that there is a perfection of <hi>de ree</hi> which they have not attained, or that there are more degrees ſtill to be ſought, ſo long as they expect another ſtate above in Glory: And we do not deny to them that perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in its <hi>kind,</hi> which every man (we hold as well as they) does, and muſt attaine unto, that is ſaved. The great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty will be onely in a right underſtanding of what <hi>kind</hi> of perfection it is, which is to be agreed upon by both.</p>
            <p>In the way for the underſtanding whereof, I muſt lay down this note, that when the Scripture ſpeaks of any good man or woman that <hi>fears God,</hi> or walk <hi>righteouſly;</hi> it is all one in Holy Language as the being <hi>Perfect</hi> is. <hi>Noah</hi> is ſaid to be a juſt Man and <hi>perfect</hi> and one that walked with God. <hi>Job</hi> a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99861:6"/>man perfect and upright, and one that feared God and eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed evil. To be a juſt Man then, a righteous man, a man that fears God, is in Scripture to be a perfect man: and to be a perfect man is to be a juſt man, a righteous man, one that fears God and eſchews evil. They are terms I ſay aequivalent in Scripture account. <hi>Bleſſed is the Man that walketh not in the Council of the ungodly, nor ſtandeth in the way of Sinners.</hi> The man that walketh not in the Council or way of the wicked, is <hi>the perfect man</hi> in other places of the Pſalmes. It is a full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, that we have of <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth. They were both Righteous before God, walking in all the commandements and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Lord blameleſs.</hi> Now if theſe friends will be contented with ſuch a Perfection in its <hi>kind</hi> as was in <hi>Noah,</hi> in <hi>Job,</hi> in <hi>Jacob,</hi> in <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the good Kings, the Prophets, in the Church of Corinth (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6.) Coloſſe. (<hi>Col.</hi> 1.28.), in <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and is indeed in every man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man once Converted, differing nevertheleſs in <hi>degree</hi> one above another, then ſhall we and they in the end be lead to a perfect accomodation.</p>
            <p>There is in the laſt place therefore, a double <hi>kind</hi> of that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which belongs to the ſtate of this life. A Perfection ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>covenant of Nature:</hi> and a perfection accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Covenant of Grave.</hi> When God made his Creatures, he appointed an order for them, in reference to which they are all ſaid to obey the Law of their Creation. Man being endued with a reaſonable Soul muſt have the knowledge of this Law, ſo far as concerns his part in it, and conſequently his reaſon alone could direct him every thing whatſoever (except of poſitive inſtitution) he was to do in order to that end unto which he was Created. Upon this does ariſe the Law of Nature, which when he was to obſerve as the condition of his Happineſs and Gods favour, or the continuance of both, that law muſt be alſo a Covenant, and that is the Covenant of Nature or Works. This Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing broken, and we rendred too impotent for it, it pleaſed God for Chriſts ſake to vouchſafe another, wherein he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes his favour and life upon lower Terms as is ſuitable to our falen ſtate. Now as a conformity to the Covenant of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is mans Righteouſneſs, and when there is no flaw therein his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99861:7"/>Perfection according to <hi>that</hi> Covenant: ſo a conformity to the terms of <hi>Grace</hi> is our righteouſneſs according to <hi>this</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and when there is nothing wanting in our coming up fully to thoſe terms (as if there be, it will not ſerve our turn), it muſt be our perfection. And here then is that Perfection upon which we are to be reconciled. Not a perfection which conſiſts in doing every thing in the Earth we are bound to do: but a perfection that notwithſtanding our many failings, is not wanting in coming up to the Terms which God accepts for Righteouſneſs to everlaſting Salvation, in the Covenant of the Goſpel. There is a <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> declared or ſet forth under the new Teſtament in oppoſition to <hi>Works</hi> (which I have mentioned in my Paper of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and explained to my content in my laſt paper of the <hi>Covenants</hi>), and it is according to this Righteouſneſs, the World is to know, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks (N B), when it makes <hi>Noah, Job, Daniel, Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> or any other, juſt men, righteous men, and perfect men in the ſight of God: When elſe, there is no <hi>fleſh</hi> before the infinite Holineſs that is <hi>clean,</hi> or that could be juſtified and ſtand in judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hear O Houſe of Iſrael, is not my wayes equal? When the wicked turneth from his wickedneſs and doeth that which is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and right be ſhall ſave his Soul.</hi> This is ſaid to be equal with God. <hi>If we confeſs our ſins, he is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins and cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs.</hi> Not onely merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but juſt. In like manner, <hi>God is not unrighteous to forget your work and labour of love which ye have ſhewn towards his Name.</hi> Again, <hi>it is a righteous thing with God to recomperce to you who are troubled reſt when Chriſt ſhall be revealed from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Henceforth there is laid up for me <hi>a Crown of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which the Righteous God ſhall give me.</hi> If God, it ſeemes, from ſuch Scriptures as theſe, ſhould put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the penitent ſinner and others, he would not be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous according to that righteouſneſs which is aſcribed to him in theſe and the like places, although if he ſhould deſtroy the world for one tranſgreſſion, we could not accuſe him of wrong in the ſenſe of ſome others. Of what value then that notion about this <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> which after many years thoughts I have offered, in the ſaid two former papers (p. 26.27. &amp;c. of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99861:7"/>one: p. 7.8 &amp;c. of the other) I leave to Time (when it hath brought the ſame light into ſome other more authoritative pen, that is to forget from whence it came) to make the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and improvement. I will adde but thus much more, by way of ſurpluſage to it. <hi>Juſtitiam in Deo ſacra Scriptura ſaepe nominat condecentiam bonitatis ipſius, ut Scholaaſtici lequuntur. &amp; Deum juſtum vocat, quum facit ea quae congruunt ejus ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, aequitati &amp; benignitati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is no man ſinneth not,</hi> ſayes <hi>Solomon,</hi> in his Prayer at the Dedication of the Temple. This he enlarges in his Eccleſiaſtes. <hi>There is not a juſt man upon Earth, that doeth good and ſimmeth not.</hi> The Apoſtle to the Romans confirms this out of the Pſalmes; <hi>There is none that doeth good, no not one.</hi> St. <hi>James</hi> likewiſe gives his Suffrage. <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> is yet moſt poſitive. <hi>If we ſay we have no ſin we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us.</hi> On the other ſide, <hi>He that committeth ſin</hi> (ſayes the ſame Apoſtle) <hi>is of the Devil.</hi> He that is <hi>born of God keepeth himſelf that the wicked one toucheth him not.</hi> Whoſoever is <hi>born of God doeth not commit ſin: For his Seed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin, becauſe he is born of God.</hi> St. Auguſtine I remember in ſeveral places of his Books does lay ſome two or three of theſe Texts together, and offers us this ſolution. <hi>That which is born of God</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſins not.</hi> Which is as much as to ſay, There is <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>born</hi> of God in the true Chriſtian, and that which is <hi>not</hi> born of him. In other terms, no man is regenerate but in part, or ſanctified but in part. Not as if one faculty was ſanctified, and not another: But there remaines the principle of Corruption, together with the principle of Grace which is infuſed, that is both fleſh and Spirit, in the ſame perſon: And whatſoever proceeds from the one cannot be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, as whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver proceeds from the other cannot be otherwiſe. I will adde, According to the prevalency there is of any of theſe two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in the ſoul, ſo is the perſon to have his denomination. The Apoſtle therefore ſpeaking of himſelf when he <hi>did</hi> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil he <hi>would not,</hi> it is <hi>no more</hi> I (ſays he) <hi>that</hi> does it, <hi>but ſin that dwelleth in me.</hi> If it be not <hi>be</hi> then that does it, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being denominated from the will, and more generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99861:8"/>part) is ſaid to <hi>ſin not.</hi> And this I-take it, after <hi>Auſtive,</hi> is ordinarily received by Divines. Nevertheleſs, that which I propoſe here from what is ſaid, ſeems to me to be more clear and weighty. There are ſome Texts ſay that all men are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and others that the regenerated do <hi>not ſin,</hi> and the blood of Chriſt <hi>cleanſeth us from all ſin.</hi> I diſtinguiſh then of ſin. Sin is the Tranſgreſſion of a Law, and as there is a twofold Law, ſo is there a twofold Tranſgreſſion. There is the tranſgreſſion of the <hi>Law of Works:</hi> Or the tranſgreſſion of the <hi>Law of Faith</hi> Every man upon Earth does ſin againſt the Law of Works, in leaving undone what it requires, or doing what it forbids in Thought, Word or Deed, even <hi>continnually;</hi> but there is no man ſins againſt the Law of Grace, ſo, as to leave undone what that requires as the condition of life, who is ſaved. It is true, that as <hi>all Power is committed to the Son,</hi> the Law of Nature is put into Chriſts hands to be commanded by him, which together with remedying Grace, are parts of his Law. Diſtinguiſh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore between ſinning againſt one or other Precept of Chriſts Law: and ſinning againſt it as a conditional Covenant, by <hi>nonper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will be for profit, yet, to multiply the ſame matter. <hi>If thou will enter into Life</hi> (ſays Chriſt) <hi>keep the Commandements.</hi> Neithe <hi>Circumciſion nor uncircumciſion availeth any thing</hi> (ſays the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) but <hi>Faith working by love</hi> in one place, but <hi>a new Creature</hi> in another, but <hi>the keeping the Commandements of God</hi> in a third. <hi>Do we make void the Law through Faith? No, we eſtabliſhed it.</hi> That the <hi>Righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit. The Doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified.</hi> It appears by multitudes of ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as theſe, that the Law, or commandements of God are to be kept or fulfilled; that the fulfilling them is required as neceſſary to the perſon juſtified, and conſequently as the condition (which is all one) of pardon and life. To help us out here therefore, we muſt diſtinguiſh after our more ſober and beſt Divines; The Law of God may be conſidered <hi>rigidly,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: or <hi>not rigidly,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, with condeſcention to human frailty, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>meaſure</hi> in every one <hi>of the gift of Chriſt,</hi> or according to <hi>our Model,</hi> ſtrength or grace in this Life, &amp; that degree of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99861:8"/>formance God which requires of us, preciſely in the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, to the obtaining Salvation. It is in the <hi>latter</hi> the <hi>mild</hi> the <hi>gracious,</hi> not in the <hi>former</hi> the <hi>rigid</hi> ſenſe, that ſuch Texts are to be interpreted; that the Law or Commandements are fulfilled; and that the obſervation is made <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the juſtified and ſaved. That is, I ſay again, not according to the <hi>model</hi> of our ſtate of <hi>innocency,</hi> but <hi>faln</hi> eſtate; not according to the <hi>Rigour</hi> of the Law, but <hi>Equity</hi> of the Goſpel; not according to the tale of Brick or preſcript of <hi>Do this and live,</hi> but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods merciful acceptation of what we do through the meritorious obedience and oblation of Chriſt Jeſus. I muſt bring this yet more home. As the Law is taken for the Law moral or Law of Nature, the matter of the Commandement, is the ſame (I have ſaid) in the Law of Chriſt, Grace and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as in the law of Works: onely this <hi>materia praecepti,</hi> this matter required, may be conſidered as <hi>materia abſoluta,</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionata,</hi> as our <hi>duty,</hi> or as the <hi>condition</hi> of Salvation. There is no man keeps the Commandements of Chriſt ſo as never to faile in any thing of his <hi>duty:</hi> But every Child of God keeps them ſo as they are made the <hi>condition</hi> of Life in the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. When a man then performes the Covenant, he muſt be judged Righteous according to that Covenant. As there is nothing lacking in that performance to the Terms, he is Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; and as he is Righteous and Perfect, he <hi>ſins not;</hi> that is, he failes not of what is required to the performance of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition. When St. <hi>John</hi> therefore ſpeaks of <hi>ſinning not,</hi> we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how he counterpoiſes <hi>committing ſin</hi> with being <hi>Righteous</hi> or <hi>doing Righteouſneſs</hi> in the ſame Chapter. The true Chriſtian <hi>ſins not</hi> ſo as oppoſes his <hi>being Righteous,</hi> he <hi>commits not ſin,</hi> as is contradictory to <hi>doing Righteouſneſs.</hi> He is Righteous now we know, or doeth Righteouſneſs, onely in regard to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and he <hi>ſins not</hi> accordingly, in regard to this Covenant; that is (as I ſum all up), failes not in the performance of the condition. He performs not <hi>materiam abſolutam,</hi> the whole <hi>duty,</hi> but he performes <hi>materiam conditionatam,</hi> the whole <hi>condition</hi> of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>By the way here, when the calm Proteſtant will grant to the Papiſts ſuch a fulfilling of the Law as does conſtitute a real true
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99861:9"/>righteouſneſs, and that which is perfect or entire according to the covenant of grace, and ſo accepted of God unto Life: and the moſt violent Papiſts will grant to the Proteſtant that this righteouſneſs nevertheleſs (<hi>ſuo modo perfecta, non omni pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus caret peccato, ideo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex hac parte perfectu non eſt</hi>) is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Sin, but doeth both faile in the degree which the Law exacts, and is intermingled with many at leaſt venial tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſo that it cannot abide Gods diſtrict judgment according to the Law of works, without need of Chriſts merits &amp; Gods mercy, who does not ſee an agreement in the <hi>purpoſe</hi> and <hi>mind,</hi> where there-is yet ſo much variance in the <hi>words</hi> and <hi>pens</hi> of thoſe that contend about thoſe matters? That Juſtification is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of the like nature and iſſue, I doubt not; and it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent pretty book of Mr. <hi>Bradſhawes</hi> on that ſubject, yet does he ſeem to me, not to have touched this main thing, which I have noted once and again in my former papers to be that, the want of the notice whereof hath ſet the <hi>Papiſt</hi> and us together by the ears, and the underſtanding whereof will as preſently heal our Controverſies: to wit, That it is not by the <hi>Law of works,</hi> but by the <hi>Law of Grace</hi> that we are judged, when we ſtand before Gods Bar for Juſtification. There are but two things to be pleaded (ſayes that worthy Authour) by an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſon. Either that he hath not committed the fault: or that he hath ſatisfyed for it. <hi>No mortal</hi> (ſays he) <hi>can deviſe any other medium whereby ſuch a perſon ſhould be juſtifyed.</hi> Our practical Divines do accordingly thunder againſt ſelf Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon this foundation. If we ſtand on our own Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (ſay they) then muſt we be able to ſatisfy God for our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſins, and cleanſe our hearts for the time to come ſo as to be perfect in his ſight. But this is a miſtake. That there is a righteouſneſs of ours that we muſt not wholly caſt away in our Juſtification, appeares from the Pſalmiſt, when he tells us by the rule of contrarys, that it is the <hi>righteous</hi> and the righteous onely, that ſhall <hi>ſtand in Judgment.</hi> There is a third plea therefore, which is the onely true plea which muſt be brought, and made good or we periſh; and that is, not that we are faultleſs or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect according to the law of works (either in our ſelves or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother): but that we are juſtifyable by the covenant of mercy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99861:9"/>as performers of the condition, and that this righteouſs though imperfect is acceptable through the merits of our Redeemer. For the buſines then of Satisfaction, it muſt be treated a little otherwiſe then Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> does it, and others, that is, not to be made the matter, or formal reaſon, of that righteouſneſs that ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyes us (let me ſay, the <hi>whole</hi> matter or formal reaſon, for I may be out elſe on the otherſide ſeeing <hi>Chriſts merits,</hi> our <hi>faith</hi> or evangelical obedience, and <hi>pardon</hi> have all their proper parts and office in it): but it muſt be underſtood mainly to ſerve the honour and juſtice of God, as Rector and Law giver, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to his dealing with us otherwiſe then according to the Law of our creation as elſe he was bound: for upon this ſcore were the ſufferings of Chriſt <hi>penall,</hi> and undergone in <hi>our ſtead,</hi> to wit, that <hi>by meanes of death for the redemption of us from the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of the firſt Covenant,</hi> a new Law or Covenant might be brought in, according to which we are to be judged. And when it is at that bar we muſt ſtand, we eaſily know both what that righteouſneſs is which muſt be pleaded, and for whoſe worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſake (ſo inconſiderable otherwiſe as it is) it ſhall be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto remiſſion and life everlaſting.</p>
            <p>To return, the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Law does tell us, that he that breakes but <hi>one of the commandements</hi> is guilty of all; and the reaſon he renders is, becauſe he requires that <hi>one,</hi> that required the <hi>reſt.</hi> The meaning is, God gave his whole Law to man for a Covenant, and if one part onely be tranſgreſſed, the condition of that covenant is broken as well as if all were tranſgreſſed. For otherwiſe, he that hath layen with a woman is not therefore to be accuſed for mnrder; nor he that hath ſworn an oath, is therefore guilty of theft. We muſt underſtand the like in reference to the Law of faith, or covenant of grace, and its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. Let a mans ſins be what they will, ſo long as the condition be performed, he may according to this Law be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no tranſgreſſour. In the one, a man hath committed no theft no adultery nor idolatry, and yet in the ſenſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle he is <hi>guilty of all,</hi> In the other he hath bin an idolater, an adulterer, a thief (<hi>ſuch were ſome of you but you, are juſtified</hi>), and he is guilty of none. The reaſon in both I ſay is, the condition ſtill in the <hi>one</hi> is broken, but performed in the <hi>other.</hi> As we
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99861:10"/>diſtinguiſh of the Law, <hi>Quâ faedus, &amp; Quâ regula:</hi> ſo may we of the performance, <hi>Sub genere officii, &amp; Sub genere conditionis.</hi> Though we fail in our <hi>Duty,</hi> we fulfill the <hi>Condition,</hi> as have ſaid already.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, it is not to be forgotten what is ſaid of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> that <hi>his heart was perfect, that he kept Gods Commandements, and that he ſinned not but in the matter of</hi> Uriah. And how I pray was that? Do not we read of <hi>Davids</hi> Paſſion, his Lying, his Numbring the people, his dealing with <hi>Mephiboſheth?</hi> was there no ſin indeed that <hi>David</hi> did commit beſides this? what makes him then complain ſo much, that he was <hi>born in Iniquity,</hi> and that his <hi>ſins were more than the hairs upon his head?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, there are ſins conſiſtent with ſincerity, and inconſiſtent with it. Sins inconſiſtent with ſincerity are breaches both of the Law of Works, and Covenant of Grace, and that <hi>ſub ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne conditionis:</hi> Sins conſiſtent with it, are tranſgreſſions indeed of the Law, but <hi>ſub hac ratione,</hi> no breach of this Covenant. <hi>Davids</hi> ſins of the firſt ſort were very many, and his acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments pious and true: <hi>Davids</hi> ſins of the latter ſort was but only in that matter, and otherwiſe it is ſaid that he <hi>ſinned not.</hi> To be clear as I goe, even for <hi>that matter,</hi> As <hi>I</hi> have diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed between the breach of our <hi>duty,</hi> and the <hi>condition;</hi> or of the <hi>preceptiue</hi> part of the law of grace, and the <hi>conditional:</hi> So muſt <hi>I</hi> diſtinguiſh <hi>this breach of the condition,</hi> into that which may be <hi>pro tempore,</hi> making the puniſhment ſo far due, as that God may cut off the Sinner and damne him: or elſe <hi>final</hi> alſo, making it peremptorily and remedileſly due, which will be ever executed by him. <hi>There is a ſin unto death, and a ſin not unto death,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle. A ſin <hi>againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever inſtance there may be, in which ſuch a ſin hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, as in the obſtinacy of the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt Chriſt, that rather than they would believe, they would impute his Miracles to the Devil, the general nature of this ſin does lye in this, that it is ſuch, as is inconſiſtent with, and excluſive of the performance of the terms which are required unto pardon and life. The <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament</hi> are one, and this is to ſin <hi>(N. B.)</hi> againſt the <hi>New Teſtament. De peccato ad mortem quoniam non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſum eſt, poſſunt diverſa ſentiri; Ego autem dico id eſſe pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99861:10"/>fidem quae per dilectionem operatur deſerere uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad mertem, Concerning the ſin unto death, becauſe it is not expreſſed, divers things may be thought of it; but I ſay that ſin is this, to deſert</hi> (or never come up to) <hi>that faith which worketh by love, unto death.</hi> Auguſtine. <hi>De Cor. &amp; gra.</hi> c. 12. It muſt be demanded then, what ſhall we think of <hi>David in the matter,</hi> wherein he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to have <hi>ſinned? I</hi> ſay that <hi>David</hi> (according to our Brittiſh Divines in the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi>) in that preſent ſtate, could not have been ſaved, if he had died: but God having E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected <hi>David,</hi> provided Repentance for him, that he could not dye in that eſtate. There is a ſin therefore which is inconſiſtent with ſincerity of heart, or the terms of grace, at <hi>preſent;</hi> or ſuch a ſin, or ſins, which are <hi>excluſive</hi> of it. This <hi>I</hi> ſaid in other words but now. The latter only are ſins unto death. The breach of the Covenant of grace <hi>ſub ratione conditionis</hi> is that ſin, and when final, that alone which is unpardonable. <hi>I</hi> reaſſume, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſins conſequently, they be which any man commits, if they be not ſuch as are incompatible with Sincerity, Repentance, and Faith, they are fins againſt the Law, and our pardon is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed: but they are no breach (<hi>ſub hac ratione, I</hi> muſt intend ſtill) of the Law of Grace, no ſin unto death, or no ſin as can hinder the perſon from being judged as <hi>righteous</hi> by that Law or Covenant, and to be accepted accordingly unto everlaſting Salvation.</p>
            <p>And now Sirs! Behold here a kind of Heaven opened to you, <hi>I</hi> mean to you who are the Children of God, and fear his Name, where all your ſins and iniquities are removed, and where every one of you are <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>ſin not.</hi> For this is the benefit and fruit of Chriſts Death and Redemption, that he hath delivered you from that Law which you break, and would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn you for every breach; and he hath brought you under a new Law, the Law of Grace, which requires nothing of you, but what <hi>ſub rat one Conditionis</hi> you do keep, for he gives his holy Spirit herein, to enable you to the performance. So that, it is not only your ſins are <hi>done away,</hi> that is <hi>not imputed,</hi> or <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given</hi> (<hi>The Iniquities of</hi> Judah, it is faid, <hi>ſhall be ſought for, and not found</hi>), but this Covenant hath nothing to lay to your charge. <hi>And you that were ſometimes alienated, hath he now reconciled in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99861:11"/>the body of his fleſh, through death, to preſent you holy and unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and unreprovable in his ſight, if ye continue in the Faith, grounded and ſetled, and be not moved away from the hope of the Coſpel.</hi> And thus we are come to our period. We grant a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which Divines call <hi>Evangelical</hi> to the Quaker, that is an integrity of heart and life which the Goſpel requires of every man that ſhall be ſaved. If theſe Friends will have more (who have not underſtood perhaps before, how much indeed this is, and what truly they impugne), then they muſt come to that our Divines call <hi>Legal</hi> righteouſneſs or perfection, which is to live ſo, as never to break any of Gods precepts, both <hi>ratione officii, &amp; conditiouis;</hi> and if they will maintain this, either that they have it (or have attain'd it) in themſelves, or that it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to others unto ſalvation, <hi>I</hi> ſhall tenderly offer them theſe enſuing Arguments, Reaſons, or Conſideratious for reclaiming them from ſo deſperate an opinion.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, Be it known, that in the <hi>Dioſpolitan</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, <hi>An. Do.</hi> 415. this was one of <hi>Pelagius</hi> errours which was there Condemned. <hi>Filios Dei non poſſe vocari, niſi qui omni modo abſque omni peccato fuerint effecti. That they cannot be called Gods Sons, who are not in all regards, without any manner of ſin.</hi> Which errour alſo <hi>Pelagius</hi> himſelf there retracted.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place it is worthy our knowing, what was the ground or reaſon of his conviction. becauſe it is like that the ſame conſideration or argument may prevail upon one or other (and more then ſo) of this Sect, that have but the like rational judgments. <hi>Nono fatetur filios dei poſſe vocari illos qui quotidie d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cunt dimitte nobis debita noſtra, quod &amp; utique veraciter non dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſi eſſent omnino abſque peccato. To the nineth Article, he confeſſes that they may be the Sons of God, who ſay daily, forgive us our Treſpaſſes, which verily they could not ſay, if they were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without ſin.</hi> The Fathers of that Council urged this upon him, that if none could be born of God that were not altogether perfect, then muſt none of Chriſts Diſciples be his Children; for how could they pray to him to forgive their debts, if they had no ſin to be forgiven? How could they pray daily for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, if they were any day without tranſgreſſion? <hi>Nathaniel</hi> was one of the Diſciples of whom it is ſaid, he was <hi>without guile,</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99861:11"/>conſequently as perfect as any Quaker dare preſume of himſelf; and yet <hi>Nathaniel</hi> as well as <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> as well as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true Believer, are taught by theſe words of their Lord, that they have need of daily forgiveneſs. It is ſufficient to this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, if <hi>that</hi> Prayer be held but a <hi>pattern,</hi> and no <hi>form,</hi> as ſome will have it; ſo long as they do not <hi>I</hi> hope, yet think they may ſcratch it out of their Bibles, becauſe they leave it unſaid.</p>
            <p>In the third place, this opinion is againſt the uniform, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſtream of Gods word, and the writings of holy men, which ſtill run thus, that we are ſinners, that we muſt all repent, and that we muſt always be renewing our repentance, in making our Prayers, Confeſſions, Supplications, Doing our Almes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good works, and reſting on Chriſt for grace and pardon. Without this ſuppoſition, the whole courſe of our Religion as Chriſtian, will ſink for want of a foundation. <hi>Theſe things write I to you, that you ſin not; and if any man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father, who is a propitiation for our ſins, and alſo for the ſius of the world.</hi> There is <hi>our</hi> ſins, St. <hi>John's</hi> ſins, that need an Advocate as well as the world. When <hi>Ezekiel</hi> is picking out three of the moſt holy men that ever were (which inſtance <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> alſo uſes) he names <hi>Daniel, Noah,</hi> and <hi>Job.</hi> Of <hi>Noah</hi> we have the record of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that he was overtaken. Of <hi>Job,</hi> we have his own acknowledgment. <hi>If I juſtifie my ſelf, my own mouth. ſhall condemn me; if I ſay I am perfect, it ſhall prove me perverſe.</hi> Of <hi>Daniel,</hi> we have a whole Chapter where he is praying and confeſſ:ing <hi>his ſin</hi> (as himſelf ſpeaks) <hi>and the ſins of his people. What is man</hi> (ſays <hi>Eliphaz</hi>) <hi>that he ſhould be Clean, and he that is born of a Woman, that he ſhould be Righteous? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold he putteth no truſt in his Saints, and the Heavens are not clean in his ſight; and how much more abominable and filthy is man, who drinketh Iniquity as water? We are all unclean</hi> (ſays the Church, ſutably to this in <hi>Iſay</hi>) <hi>and all our Righteouſneſſes are as filthy raggs.</hi> There is one Text moſt full, as moſt common, not to be omitted, which is that of <hi>David. Enter not into judgment with thy Servant, for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified.</hi> This is applied by the Apoſtle againſt juſtification by the deeds of the Law. If there is, or ever was, any meer mortal on Earth that lived altogether without ſin, then muſt this Text be falſe;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99861:12"/>then may ſome men living be juſtified in his ſight, though he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into diſtrict judgment with them; then may ſome fleſh liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be juſtified by works; then muſt ſalvation alone by Chriſt, and the Doctrine indeed of the whole Goſpel come to the ground. For,</p>
            <p>In the fourth place, as this is againſt ſeveral particular Texts before named, and the general current of the Scripture and holy Writers: So is it directly againſt the very drift of what the Apoſtle delivers to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Galathians.</hi> It is common for men to alleadg a few ſcattered Scriptures againſt any opinion which yet is true, and we Anſwer thoſe Scriptures: but if an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion does croſs any one Text, and much more any Epiſtle in the very ſcope and purport of it, ſuch an opinion muſt be left, or all will come to naught. It is manifeſt now that <hi>Paul</hi> in thoſe two Epiſtles is ſetting forth the Doctrine of <hi>juſtification by Faith, through our Redemption by Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> For the making this good, he firſt ſhews that all men whatſoever ſtands guilty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God of the breach of his Law. This he moſt induſtriouſly proves of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in one Chapter; of the <hi>Jews</hi> in another; and in the third, <hi>What then</hi> (ſays he) <hi>are we better than they? no, in no wiſe, for we have before proved both Jew and Gemile, that they are all under ſin.</hi> Upon this <hi>Medium,</hi> he argues, that no man therefore, either <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> can be juſtified by the Law, for then they ſhould be <hi>doers,</hi> and not <hi>breakers</hi> of it. From this truth, that they cannot be juſtified by the Law, it follows that there muſt be ſome other means of their juſtification. And this he declares (as the great concern and Goſpel he has to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver), to be by <hi>Faith, through the Redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> This is the ſum of his doctrine and arguing. We may if you will for our advantage put more together. If we are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied through Chriſts Redemption by Faith, when none of us have performed the condition which was required of us to our juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by the Law of our Creation, then muſt our juſtification be of grace or favour, as being not elſe due. And if this grace is obtained or purchaſed for us through Chriſts Redemption, then is God righteous, though he accepts of us (ſeeing it is for Chriſts ſake) without that condition. And if he is righteous in his accepting any without that condition, there muſt be ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99861:12"/>procured by Chriſt, upon which he accepts them, ſeeing all are not accepted, notwithſtanding Chriſts Redemption. That other is Faith, as the <hi>initium</hi> and foundation of all other duty, that is <hi>Faith working by Love,</hi> even that <hi>Love</hi> which <hi>fulfils the Law,</hi> and is <hi>ſhed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt given to us,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> that great aſſertour of grace ſtill ſpeaks. From hence does there appear that <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> which is ſet out in oppoſition to our Righteouſneſs by the Law, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before in its due place; which indeed is nothing elſe but this grace it ſelf, even the goodneſs, kindneſs, favour, or merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful condeſcention of God to poor Sinners, in accepting us as Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous upon other terms, then thoſe which the Law of our Nature requires, and it were but moſt juſt we ſhould have performed. Which as he grants for Chriſts ſake, ſo does he by his Spirit work in thoſe that are his choſen, that all the glory of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation may be due to him only. Now the perfection of the Quaker does quite over-throw all this which the Apoſtle teaches; and in ſhort terms, it were all one for them to ſay, Sir, we deny your Argument, and your Reaſoning. We are of opinion that all men do not break the Law of God, but that ſome are perfect in a Righteouſneſs, anſwering the Law, and therefore we have no need of any ſuch grace, or Chriſts Redemption (that is of any from Chriſt as <hi>without</hi>), or other terms, whereby we ſhould be juſtified and ſaved. The Righteouſneſs of <hi>God,</hi> or the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of <hi>Faith</hi> you ſpeak of in oppoſition to <hi>Works,</hi> is below that of <hi>ours,</hi> which we build upon for our Salvation.</p>
            <p>In the fifth place, This opinion is not conſonant with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality</hi> of Redemption. There are no greater patrons of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal grace than the Quaker. This is the <hi>excellency of his ſtrength,</hi> the <hi>Ruben</hi> of his notions. But if Chriſts Redemption lye altogether where they place it, in the bringing men off from Sin and Unrighteouſneſs unto Holineſs and Perfection, even ſuch as to live without ſin in this world, then cannot Redemption be univerſal: for the moſt of men remain in their ſins, and are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver converted; and thoſe that are, reach not to ſuch a pitch as this is; and conſequently, inſtead of Chriſts having Redeemed all the World, or whole Man-kind, there are but very ſew Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, and indeed none at all. I muſt confeſs I do not think
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99861:13"/>that the Quaker alone is in the dark about this matter. Yet theſe men I count here, are moſt of all out. They look upon the work of Chriſts Redemption to be the work of Chriſt <hi>within;</hi> ſo they ſpeak, and ſo they think altogether, and then wilfully confound <hi>Sanctification</hi> and <hi>Redemption;</hi> whereas Sanctification is a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of perſons from the world, and muſt be of <hi>ſome</hi> only, that is the <hi>Elect</hi> (ſuppoſing Election): but Redemption is of <hi>all man-kind,</hi> according to the Catechiſme, and the Scripture all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. That which Chriſt hath done for us <hi>without,</hi> and in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> is for all. He was put to death in the fleſh; his Death was for all. <hi>He taſted Death for every man.</hi> But what he does for us <hi>within,</hi> what he does in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> that is peculiar, and not alike to all; and the one muſt not be confounded with the other. It is worth our asking therefore, what Redemption and its immediate fruit to man-kind is? and this hath been diſpatcht in my paper about <hi>Redemption.</hi> The introduction of a new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and other terms for man to live by, is the main. The Quaker now does place Chriſts Redemption in bringing us up to theſe terms, the performance whereof is indeed our Goſpel-perfection; but he is here ſo miſerably out, that he both miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes the terms, or this perfection, as if it were no leſs then the fulfilling every jot of the Law it ſelf; &amp; alſo contradicts himſelf in the beſt tenent he has. For how ſhall the grace of Chriſts Redemption be univerſal, if it be placed in that which is not u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal? How ſhall Chriſts death be for <hi>all,</hi> if the great and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate effect of it, be that which only belongs to the <hi>Elect?</hi> On the other hand, our Divines we call Orthodox, do generally ſtumble upon this ſame ſtone, in their denyal of Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption to be univerſal. It is not ſufficient to them for the hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſts Redemption to be univerſal, that he hath procured that all may be ſaved, if they believe and repent, which are our new terms; unleſs he hath procured alſo that they believe and repent. But it is the Elect only do believe and repent, and therefore they hold the Redemption only of the Elect. Theſe men (how many of them ſoever they be) have not yet learned to diſtinguiſh the <hi>conditien</hi> from the <hi>perfermance;</hi> and that Chriſts Redemption does lye in procuring the <hi>condition,</hi> not <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermance,</hi> for the <hi>world.</hi> They know and will ſay that there is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99861:13"/>another condition required of us by the Law of our Creation, and if man may be juſtified without that, then muſt there be grace in the grant of this. And this grace they are then to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand more, is that grace which is ſo magnified in the (of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, the <hi>grace</hi> that came by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> as the <hi>Law</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the grace it ſelf of our Redemption. Let the Quaker then know it is not Chriſts bringing man up to the terms of God, but his bringing down God to the terms of man (that is, to ſuch as are ſutable to his falne eſtate), wherein the great work he hath done for us, is to be fixed. And let theſe Orthodox know the ſame likewiſe, that it muſt be therefore his procuring ſalvation upon our Faith and Repentance; and not Repentauce and Faith for our Salvation, which is the direct and immediate effect of his Redemption. But what? <hi>Is</hi> not our Believing and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance then the fruit and purchaſe of Chriſts death? Be not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended Sirs, our Faith and Repentance are a fruit of his Spirit. the work of our Sanctification, and proceeds from Election. See my reaſons in <hi>p.</hi> 29. of my firſt paper.</p>
            <p>In the ſixth place. <hi>It</hi> ſeems to me, that the want of more light to diſcern between truth and truth, is the occaſion of perſiſting to theſe Friends in their errour, and to us in our oppoſition. <hi>It</hi> is true what we ſay, that no men but <hi>ſin;</hi> and it is true what they ſay, the Regenerate <hi>ſin not:</hi> The Scripture ſays both. The Child of God <hi>ſins not,</hi> ſo as that ſin hath <hi>dominion</hi> over him when he ſins. The prevailing intereſt of his Soul is for God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the fleſh and the world, and ſo long he is right in Gods ſight; right, <hi>Righteous,</hi> or <hi>Perfect,</hi> according to the Law of <hi>Crace;</hi> although there be a thousand things wherein he might do more good, or leſs evil than he does, and ſo is imperfect, unrighteous, and a manifold ſinner according to the Law of <hi>work.</hi> The truth is, there is ſomething here at the bottom, which theſe men ſee, and our common Proteſtants do not ſee, which makes them think they ſee more than we, and more than they do ſee. <hi>It</hi> is this. that there can be indeed no juſtification of any, but according to ſome Law, where we can plead that we are innocent, or that we have kept that Law, and that perfectly, ſo that we are <hi>Righteous</hi> according to it. This being ſeen, they come on too faſt, that they ſin not; before they have learned to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99861:14"/>diſtinguiſh between Law and Law, Righteouſneſs and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Juſtification and Juſtification, Sin and Sin. They ſin not, they are Righteous, and by that Righteouſneſs <hi>I</hi> muſt ſay with them (where they have our Divines on the blind ſide) are juſtified, to wit, according to the <hi>Law of Faith,</hi> or as they are judged at the Throne of Grace; but they do ſin, they are Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, and no fleſh living can be juſtified according to the <hi>Law of Works,</hi> or at the bar of the Ten Commandements. When the Apoſtle argues againſt juſtification by the Law, he proves none can be juſtified by it, becauſe all do break it. Thoſe that will follow truth ſhall argue as ſtrongly; if we be ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ified by grace, then we muſt be righteous and perfect, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Law</hi> of it. The Orthodox are quite out that will have any juſtified without a Righteouſneſs that is perfect accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law that juſtifies him (to wit, in regard to the <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional,</hi> though not the <hi>preceptive</hi> part of it). The Quaker is quite out that will have this Righteouſneſs perfect according to the ten Commandements which does not juſtifie him. The lover of Truth and Mediocrity will have every man have the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a perfect heart for his juſtification, and yet no man be juſtified but by the grace of God, through the Redemption which we have in Chriſt Jeſus. There is pardon of ſin, and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; theſe may be diſtinguiſhed, not divided. Pardon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the law of works; juſtification to the law of Faith, or the Goſpel. <hi>For this cauſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>he is the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour of the New Teſtament, that by means of death for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the Tranſgreſſions that were under the firſt Teſtament, they which are called may receive the promiſe of eternal Inheritance.</hi> The firſt Covenant originally is that of <hi>Nature,</hi> and the <hi>firſt Teſtament</hi> belonging to the Jew, <hi>repreſented</hi> that firſt Covenant, and the Tranſgreſſions for which Chriſt ſhed his blood, are our ſins only againſt that Covenant: <hi>If</hi> there be any body ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the new Covenant, there is no Redemption for ſuch. We have a <hi>pardon</hi> then in reference to the law of works, but we are <hi>juſtified</hi> in reference to the law of Faith. To wit, <hi>If</hi> we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed as Tranſgreſſors of the <hi>Law,</hi> we may confeſs it that we are guilty, and plead our pardon through Chriſts Redemption; but if we are charged as Tranſgreſſors of the <hi>law of grace,</hi> we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99861:14"/>muſt not plead our ſelves guilty but righteous, and ſuch as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly come up to the terms required in the Goſpel, or elſe we are gone. It is true, Chriſt hath purchaſed forgiveneſs, but it is upon condition. <hi>Pardon</hi> is of the Tranſgreſſions of the Law, but this <hi>condition</hi> is of Righteouſneſs according to the Goſpel, and our juſtification lyes in the performance of the condition.</p>
            <p>In the ſeaventh place, This Opinion, inſtead of leading theſe friends to the <hi>Spirit</hi> and the <hi>Life</hi> as they ſpeak, does lead them <hi>from</hi> both, and bring them back to the <hi>letter,</hi> and the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and <hi>miniſtration of death.</hi> To underſtand this, The Apoſtle we know does diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Letter</hi> and the <hi>Spirit.</hi> The <hi>Letter killeth, the Spirit giveth Life.</hi> This diſtinction is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed otherwhere by the <hi>Law of the Spirit of life,</hi> and the <hi>Law of ſin and death.</hi> The Law of <hi>Faith,</hi> and Law of <hi>Works.</hi> The Covenant of <hi>Nature,</hi> and Covenant of <hi>Grace.</hi> The Law of Works is call'd the <hi>Letter,</hi> as having been writ in ſtone, and is the miniſtration of death, <hi>the Law of ſin and death,</hi> or that which <hi>killeth,</hi> becauſe there is none but break it, and ſo are guilty of fin and death by it. The Covenant of grace is the <hi>Law of Faith,</hi> that being the condition of it; it is the <hi>Law of the ſpirit of life,</hi> or the miniſtration of life for the contrary reaſon, becauſe we are enabled through grace or this ſpirit, to the performance of this Law, ſo as to be Righteous according to it, and live by it. <hi>The juſt man ſhall live by his Faith.</hi> And unto the Law of the ſpirit of life, is added, <hi>in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> becauſe it is he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured this Law for us, which is indeed the great benefit of our Redemption. Now while the Spirit is given us for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the condition of this Covenant, (it being the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> not the <hi>Law</hi> which is the miniſtration of the Spirit) it is a great miſtake in theſe Friends to expect ſuch help from it, as to perform the condition of the Covenant of Nature, or Law of Works. The Spirit indeed does help us, but it is to keep his own Law, the <hi>Law of the Spirit,</hi> and that Law whereby we may have <hi>life.</hi> If we do look to fulfill the Covenant of Nature, we muſt return to our original Righteouſneſs, and our free will which we loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> and that is to go from the <hi>Spirit</hi> to our ſelves who are but <hi>fleſh.</hi> But what? Is not the Law of God the rule of our lives? and does not the Spirit of God lead us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99861:15"/>to rule, and bring us to a conformity to his law? I anſwer no doubt of it: but that is a conformity ſo far as reaches the fulfilling the terms of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but not thoſe of <hi>Works.</hi> The law of grace does require a ſincere walking before Go! in all his Commandements, and the Spirit of God does certainly help us ſo far as we ſin not againſt that ſincerity, or ſin, no ſins inconſiſtent with theſe terms: but the ſpirit is not given to bring us up to the terms of the Law, and that we ſhould not ſin at all. <hi>What ſhall we ſay that</hi> Abraham <hi>as pertaining to the fleſh hath found?</hi> By the <hi>fleſh</hi> we are to underſtand <hi>works</hi> as appears in the next verſe: and ſo is the <hi>ſpirit</hi> oppoſed to the <hi>fleſh,</hi> as it is oppoſed to the <hi>law of works.</hi> If we ſeek therefore for a Righteouſneſs by our works, that is according to that law, we ſhall find what <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did, as <hi>pertaining to the fleſh.</hi> We ſhall find no ſuch matter. <hi>O ye fooliſh Galathians</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>having begun in the ſpirit, are ye now made pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fect by the fleſh?</hi> The <hi>Galathians</hi> belike who had received the doctrine of grace by <hi>Paul,</hi> were come to be ſeduced to the opinion that they muſt keep <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, or elſe they could not be ſaved; and this is their ſeeking to be made <hi>perfect by the fleſh.</hi> The <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>nature</hi> are Synony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous terms, and as in reſpect of thoſe who were <hi>Jews by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> the works of the Law, as given by <hi>Moſes</hi> are called fleſh: ſo muſt the works of the Law, as a Covenant by Nature, be fleſh in reſpect to the reſt of man-kind. If the Quaker then is come to ſeek life by ſuch a following his light as muſt anſwer the Covenant of Nature it ſelf; that is by a perfection as is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin againſt the Law, he is plainly under the notion of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> brought at laſt to the <hi>fleſh</hi> for what he ſeeks.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, It is an ancient ſaying that he who looks but one thing is eaſily miſlead. It ſeems that theſe Friends do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that our doctrine which oppoſes perfection does ſerve for the boulſtring up men in their ſins, and lull them into ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that though they live and dye in their wickedneſs, they muſt be ſaved; and this being taught eſpecially among us Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, who believe that we are juſtified by Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without works, does appear very deſtructive to many ſouls, which makes them out of an intention which we may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe zealous for godlineſs, and the promotion of a good life,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99861:15"/>to fall on our Divines with ſo much tragical exclamation as they do on this point: When in the mean time they neither have conſidered what our Divines do ſay that removes all ground for any ſuch abuſe; nor what indeed are the conſequences of their own doctrine, which under <hi>Pelagianiſme, Donatiſme,</hi> and the like names, hath been ſo often exploded, as utterly intolerable in the Church of God. For their conviction in both theſe, <hi>I</hi> would not in the way have them ignorant what doctrine it was <hi>Paul</hi> Preached, and upon which the like conſequences was faſtened by ſome perſons at that time, that if grace abounded, they might therefore live in ſin: <hi>It</hi> is but the ſame doctrine of Gods abounding free grace, mercy, and forgiveneſs through Chriſt to poor Sinners that our Divines do bring againſt the doctrine of perfection (ſetting the unſound ſenſe of imputed Righteouſneſs aſide), which <hi>Paul</hi> Preached, and pleaded againſt thoſe who would bring in the works of the Law for their juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. And when theſe Friends have pondered the Apoſtles anſwer to what was alleadged againſt him, there will need but little more to be ſaid by us here unto the ſame. There are two things particularly our Divines teach. The one is, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding grace be imperfect in this life, there is no man may ſin for all that, in any the leaſt thing whatſoever: That is, though our holineſs be imperfect, yet is it our <hi>duty</hi> to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and we are ſtill to be preſſed to <hi>go on to perfection.</hi> The other is that a ſtate of grace will not ſtand with any ſin in <hi>domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> That is, that whoſoever does willingly and wilfully live in any known ſin without Repentance unto death, he cannot be ſaved. And what is the reaſon then, when theſe two things are ſtill taught, that theſe men ſhould charge the Orthodox with that conſequence which they do ſo effectually diſclaim? Let them look into any practical Books of ours, and ſee if obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which is univerſal, be not given as the chief note ſtill of an upright man, and of that Faith which is ſaving? And what would they themſelves now ſay more? <hi>If</hi> this rather, without ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as ſo far as human frailty, according to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral complexions, circumſtances, and temptations of perſons, by infinite goodneſs and wiſdom will be allowed) be not more ſtrict than can be borne. Will it not indeed ſuffice that a man is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99861:16"/>upright before God in his <hi>deſires</hi> and <hi>endeavours</hi> after per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that is the <hi>having reſpect to all his commandments,</hi> unleſs he alſo be perfect, and his works overtake his will? What then ſhall become of the generation of the moſt juſt? Let us ſee when this one inconvenience they apprehend as conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to our doctrine is wiped off, whether the ſeveral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences that follow their doctrine doe not require more heed.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, where they ſay our doctrine does lead men into ſecurity, remiſneſs of life, neglect of their duty, a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courſe: how muſt their doctrine hurle men into deſpaire, and lead them by that to the caſting off the whole care of God and their ſouls altogether? There is no meanes under Heaven ſo likely to bring a man to give up all, as to make him deſperate. If it will not ſerve a man for his acceptance with God that he is ſincere in his deſires and endeavours of walking before him, unleſs he attain to perfection, or to a life that is wholy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin in this world, then muſt the heart of the moſt holy and mortified man upon earth be quite broke and diſcouraged for ever. <hi>There is mercy with thee</hi> (sayes David) <hi>that thou maiſt be feared,</hi> If God were nor good and merciful to conſider mans frailty, to pardon his ſhortneſſes and imperfections, and bear with him, we ſhould not <hi>fear</hi> him, that is worſhip or ſerve him, for it were to no purpoſe to go about it, ſeeing we could never pleaſe him. Alas! that theſe folkes did but know what they do, when they bring in ſuch doctrine, who themſelves muſt tremble to be judged by it. O ye <hi>fooliſh Galathians! who hath bewiched you,</hi> that you ſhould depart from that comfort and peace which ſome of you I believe ſometimes had in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting on Chriſt altogether for your pardon and reconciliation with God, that you ſhould be brought now to the works of the Law, and theſe terms, that if you <hi>do them</hi> you ſhall <hi>live in them?</hi> Is there any indeed of you think that you are able, and doe <hi>continue in all things that are written in the book of the Law,</hi> or in all things that are written in the <hi>tables of your hearts</hi> to do them? And are you ignorant that upon that account, and that alone, that none do, or are able to do ſo the Apoſtle tells you, <hi>As many as are of the works of the Law are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99861:16"/>under the curſe?</hi> Alas Sirs! what mean you, when we are under the miniſtration of the New-Teſtament, which brings the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> (where the Spirit is there is liberty), and <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes</hi> (for by the law of faith the Chriſtian hath a righteouſneſs to plead and to be juſtified by) and ſo <hi>life,</hi> you ſhould be ready to return into a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or <hi>Natural</hi> bondage, to ſeek for it from that onely which can bring <hi>death,</hi> and is the miniſtration of ſin and condemnation?</p>
            <p>Secondly, I wiſh, into whatſoever conſequence our doctrine may lead ſome of our people, that your doctrine does not lead your people into ſome evils more ſecret and ſpiritual, but much more deadly to the ſoul, then our ordinary ſins are. When we ſhall ſee a perſon (ſuppoſe ſome Youth of either Sex) as ſoon as they are but wrought over to your party, be ready im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to look on all the reſt of people at a diſtance to a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect, nay even to a contempt of the moſt grave, ſerious, holy of profeſſours which they before converſed withall, and ſo talk to them as if they knew nothing ſtreight in compariſon of them, but as men altogether in the dark without <hi>light</hi> or <hi>life</hi> were to be ſeparated from, till they arrive to <hi>their</hi> attainment, or higher ſtate. I know not what you your ſelves may <hi>ſay</hi> at ſuch a ſight, nor what ſome others may <hi>think</hi> who paſſe it by with a ſmile or jeſt at the folly, or elſe with wrath, ſcorn, and indignation at the inſolence, and infinite preſumption: but I for my part muſt profeſſe it, as to my own ſoul, to be a matter of a very deep, ſad, and afflictive apprehenſion, to behold ſuch a <hi>novice</hi> falling into the <hi>condemnation of the Devil.</hi> Alas! what is it if the Devil himſelf were again in his firſt ſtation that he would ſay, but I am now in that Seraphical ſtate, as is above all Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims, Thrones, Dominions, Angells, Archangells. I am like God, and none of theſe are like to me. If pride, if Spiritual pride, if the moſt damnable pride, to be proud of Gods grace, which conſiſts in ſuch a monſtrous overweening conceit of a mans ſelf as this, that he is <hi>perfect</hi> (and in one too who hath ſcarce broken the ſhell yet in Religion), to the neglect, deſpiſing, continual cenſuring, and ſetting at naught of others, be no evil, then may the prudent, the ſober, and pious amongſt you who are beſt able to ſee, and to mourn for the miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99861:17"/>of your ſect, have leſſe reaſon to fear the tendency of this doctrine of <hi>Perfection:</hi> But if it be the way of Chriſtians to be humble, to look on themſelves as vile, as nothing, to live alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether on dependance upon God, each man in lowlines of mind eſteeming of others better then themſelves, then will it be your duty to have more care of what you are to rebuke, and of what you are to teach. <hi>Leaſt that which is lame be turned out of the way, and that which is weak be deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, There is the danger, that exceeding danger in the very entainment of this opinion, that I am afraid at my heart it cannot conſiſt (if prevalent) with the grace of God, and juſtification of a ſinner by Chriſt. It is a high text, that of the Apoſtle. <hi>Behold I Paul ſay unto you that if you be circumciſed Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing.</hi> Circumciſion was a bond to the keeping the whole law, and if the <hi>Galathians</hi> upon the opinion that the Law muſt be kept for their juſtification were circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, they are like as it ſeemes here to bring themſelves into that condition as to ſtand or fall by it. Let them look to it then, if they break but one of the commandements, to the whole whereof they are debtors, the bond is forfeit. The like inſtance is that we have in the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves. God had given them his Law, which was indeed to direct them in a holy life; but the chief end of it was through conviction of ſin to drive them to God for his pardon and grace, which was to be received through the promiſe, by their Faith. Now the <hi>Jews</hi> being ignorant of this end, look to the Law only for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and are loſt. I am really afraid at my very heart Sirs, leaſt your caſe be the very ſame in effect with theſe. You have the Goſpel Preached, and if you accept of your pardon through Chriſt there is no more required, but the walking ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely before him, and acknowledging him your <hi>Advocate</hi> if you ſin, and you may be ſafe; but you have taken up an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that the whole Law muſt be kept, that you muſt live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, and unleſs you come up to this pitch, you cannot be ſaved. What is here then, I ſay, but ſuch an Opinion as that of the <hi>Galathians,</hi> and ſuch an eſtabliſhing of your own Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as the <hi>Jews</hi> was; only with this difference indeed in both, that it is <hi>more.</hi> For the Righteouſneſs of the Law, as given by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99861:17"/>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> was not thought by them ſo ſtrict as we know it to be, as given by <hi>Nature.</hi> And if they ſhall ſtand for their lives up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe terms, who is not apprehenſive of the danger of ſuch Doctrine? <hi>For I teſtifie again to every man, that whoſoever of you are juſtified by the Law, ye are fallen from Grace.</hi> I remember when Feſtus had brought <hi>Paul</hi> out to <hi>Agrippa,</hi> and he had open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and pleaded his cauſe before him, <hi>Agrippa</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Feſtiu, This man might have been ſet at liberty, if he had not appealed to Caeſar.</hi> If theſe Friends, being at the Bar of the Goſpel, would ſtand to that grace we have there, they might be freed by courſe with other honeſt Chriſtian folks, through the Redemption which is in Chriſt Jeſus. Who hath any thing to charge upon them? But if they will appeal from thoſe terms under which we are brought by Chriſt, unto their perſection, which is the terms of the Law, to be judged by that; what can we ſay elſe, but they have appealed unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and to <hi>Caeſar</hi> muſt they go. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your perfection you have appealed, and when you ſhall be found imperfect, as all fleſh living muſt be, what ſhall become of you before the great Tribunal of God? O Lord! Thou ſeeſt mans fooliſhneſs, and knoweſt his danger. If any of theſe poor people are indeed upon ſuch a precipice, as my Soul fears for them, deliver them, ſave them from it, bring them to a right mind, that they may not depart from thy grace, to go to their own Ciſterns. <hi>They went to the Wells, and there was no Water; they returned with their Veſſels empty, and were aſhamed.</hi> We have a ſingular preſident in <hi>Job.</hi> A man may wonder ſometimes why God ſhould deal ſo ſeverely with that Saint. It was not perhaps without cauſe. <hi>Job</hi> was a holy perſon, and he knew it, he ſtood upon it; and it is poſſible he might by that temper of his, be one who in the eſtabliſhing this <hi>Righteouſneſs of his own,</hi> was apt to forget to ſubmit to the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> and that this was the very ſecret cauſe which makes him have need of ſo ſufficient a courſe to be taken for reducing him out of that danger. Friends! Let me ſpeak to you here in thoſe words which <hi>Eliphaz</hi> did to his Friend. Surely you have ſpoken in my hearing, and <hi>I</hi> have heard the voyce of your words, ſaying, <hi>We are Clean without Tranſgreſſion; we are Innocent, neither is there Iniquity in us.</hi> Let me then ſpeak to you in the words al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99861:18"/>of God. <hi>Who are theſe that darken Counſel with words without knowledge? I</hi> humbly beſeech the Lord, that what is offered here unto you, to the like end (ſuppoſing the end of the Lord to <hi>Job,</hi> herein to be ſuch), may be received with the like effect. That you may ſay, <hi>Behold we are vile, what ſhall we anſwer thee? we will lay our hands on our mouths. Once have we ſpoken, but we will not anſwer; yea twice, but we will proceed no further.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Auguſtine. Cont. Ep. Parmen. l. 2. c. 6.</bibl>
                  <p>Quamvis in quantum ex deo nati ſumus non peccemus, ineſt tamen adhuc etiam quod ex Adamo nati ſumus. Et quamdiu expectamus per patientiam corporis noſtri redemptionem, non audeamus dicere carere nos omni vitio, ne ipſa ſuperbia ſit immaniſſimum vitium. <hi>Although in ſo much as we are born of God, we ſin not, yet does there remain in us that too, which is born of</hi> Adam; <hi>and ſo long as we, through patience, do wait for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the body, we dare not ſay that we are without all ſin, leaſt that very Pride it ſelf be a moſt monſtrous ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:99861:18"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Intended more Papers under this Title of the <hi>Middle Way;</hi> but being Diſcouraged, this (I ſuppoſe) is the laſt. You have one Paper of <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Redemption,</hi> put that firſt: Another of <hi>Juſtification:</hi> A third of the <hi>Covenants, Law,</hi> and <hi>Goſpel:</hi> And this fourth of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi> Expect no more. The Bookſeller now will Bind them together. The letters <hi>(N. B.)</hi> are <hi>Nota bene. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete omnes, &amp; condonate.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. H</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Deo Gloria.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
